Hey, folks.
My name is Sydney.
I'm the product manager for the open source team at LangChain.
And today, I'm super excited to share with you
how you can build a model router in the harness
to reduce cost without sacrificing quality.
Let's jump in.
So the motivating problem for building a model router
is that frontier intelligence is really expensive.
And so if you're building agents that work at scale,
this cost can be prohibitive.
And so model routing can help to reduce cost,
theoretically without sacrificing quality if it's done well.
I have a quote here showing that model providers like
Anthropic even recommend starting with smaller models,
in this case like Claude Haiku, before graduating to a more
intelligent model like Opus, because a lot of tasks can be
done with these cheaper models.
So I'm basically assuming here that we often don't need the
best model for a lot of tasks that we ask our agent to do.
Past a certain point, you kind of hit diminishing returns
where your cost and latency are increasing,
but the quality of the outputs are not significantly better.
And ideally, an agent has good model-harness-task fit.
And what does that mean?
It means you have the right model for the job
on the intelligence and cost curve here.
And then your harness does a good job
of getting the right context to the model
for the given task at hand.
So what does a model router actually do?
It picks the right model for each task.
And so a task request comes in, and a router
has a classifier model, and then a prompt
with some criteria that help it decide what model would
be most appropriate for a given task.
So would that be a fast and cheap model, maybe something
balanced, or a performance-focused model
that's going to be slower and more expensive?
And then it selects the given model for the task,
and then that model is used to power the agent that
completes the task.
And so our test bed here was Open SWE, our open source
coding agent.
And to kind of spoil the results of the experiment here,
we were able to see a 64% reduction in median cost
per thread with no measurable change in quality.
There's four steps for building a model router,
and I'll explain them through the lens of this Open SWE
experiment that we ran.
But a little sneak peek here.
First, you need to understand the tasks
that your agent works on.
You need to understand the models available for these tasks.
Then with one and two done, you can build the router
in your agent's harness.
And it's very important to track task outcomes
so that you can understand if your router is working well.
That is reducing cost without sacrificing quality.
OK, so let's talk about step one, understanding the tasks.
The first thing that we did was try
to understand what our coding agent Open SWE is being
tasked with.
This was all done using LangSmith.
So every time our coding agent runs,
it sends a trace to LangSmith that
has a record of every step that that agent took.
And so we were able to use all of those traces
and do aggregate analysis over them
to determine what types of tasks our agent was doing.
So you can see here, unsurprisingly, for a coding
agent that code changes dominated things like feature requests,
bug fixes, and tests.
But there were also some things like design questions
and general purpose questions.
Out of all of the steps,
I would actually say that this one is the most important.
This is what you use as the foundation
for building your criteria for the router.
You know, deciding what types of tasks
should be assigned which model.
And so if you don't have a clear understanding
of this task space,
it's going to be very hard to develop an effective router.
And LangSmith, as I mentioned, was very instrumental
in helping understand this space.
I actually built a custom app on top of LangSmith
to help me better understand this trace data.
So you can see kind of the categories here
and then active agent time and observed LLM cost
filtered by different types of requests.
Overall, this was super helpful
for basically exploratory data analysis over my traces.
Also as part of step one,
I wanted to better understand
how complexity varied by task type,
knowing that we probably want a more intelligent model
for more complex tasks.
So you can see here, we measured median invocations.
So that's the number of times Open SWE was called.
And then also the median LLM cost
for these different buckets of tasks.
And then we generally rated a task as more complex
if the number of invocations were higher
or the LLM cost was higher.
And you can see kind of unsurprisingly here
that like feature work was generally more complex
than say testing work.
All right, so this part is actually quite fun.
Step two is understanding the models available
for your tasks.
So this data is pulled from the
Artificial Analysis Intelligence Index
as of September 9th, 2026,
which is when we began this experiment.
And you can see on the X-axis,
we have the cost per intelligence task.
And then on the Y-axis,
we have the Artificial Analysis Intelligence Index.
This is what we call the Pareto frontier for LLMs.
It's this set of optimal models that have a good trade-off
between like benchmark accuracy and evals
compared to cost and latency.
And so generally we want to select models along this frontier.
And then given that we were designing a model router,
we wanted to choose a small set of models here
that had some trade-offs between their speed
and intelligence index.
The models that we ended up choosing
were GLM-5.3-Flash for our fast model, GPT-5.6
Sol for our balanced model, and then GPT-6 Astra
for our performance tier.
Step three is building the router in the harness.
So we used two sources of data to decide on the criteria
for our initial version of the router.
The first was the understanding of those tasks
that we saw in step one.
And the second was the official provider guides
from OpenAI, for example, on which models
to use for which tasks.
And so you can see a couple of the descriptors
that we used for each of the criteria for a given model.
Also important to note for our router here,
the router just runs once on the thread's first message
and then selects the model for the remainder of the task.
This is different from some routers which
do this mid-flight routing.
We decided to just do a simple version
first, but when I talk about upcoming improvements or further work, mid-thread routing is covered.
So when we initially built this router in early September, we used a small LLM, specifically
GLM-5.3-Flash, to do the routing decision with structured output. But after the experiment,
Jev, a popular decision model, came out and had claims of being significantly faster and cheaper
than LLMs with more constrained decision-making powers.
And so we are now powering our Open SWE router with Jev,
the decision model.
And it's much faster and much cheaper as Jev advertised.
The last thing I'll call out on this slide
is that GLM-5.3-Flash is actually an open model.
At LangChain a while ago, we wrote a blog
about open models crossing a threshold.
We definitely think that's true.
We use open models a lot internally.
And a model router is a great opportunity
to experiment with using cheaper and faster open models
for tasks that they're more than equipped to handle.
OK.
And then for step four, you need to decide
how you're going to track your task outcomes.
There's two main ways you can do this.
The first is through offline evals.
So this is very safe.
You have repeatable comparisons and experiments
that you can run.
But the catch is that it can be a little bit hard and expensive
to develop a representative data set.
And so the faster approach here is to do an A/B test,
where you know that your live traffic is representative.
But the catch here is that we're running this experiment
for our live users, and so they may experience
a non-optimal router, which is the risk.
And so the two outcomes that we were tracking with our A/B
test were the merged PR rate.
And then also, we enabled users to provide feedback
on Open SWE runs so they could either give a thumbs up
or a thumbs down.
And so you can imagine we want to make
sure that for the 50% of threads that
run through this new router, the merged PR rate
doesn't go down significantly, and the feedback
is not significantly different either.
All right, so experiment number one, what were our results?
We had almost 500 threads.
And you can see that the median cost per thread
for the router was much lower, 64% lower.
The mean cost was also lower, and then the P90 cost per thread
was lower by 37%.
We see actually for this case more threads
from the routed version ending in a merged PR,
although the difference was not statistically significant.
And then we also see that the PR open rate
was pretty comparable across our A and B branches.
You can see on this breakdown kind of the proportion of tasks
that were sent to each of the model tiers.
So we had 34% sent to the fast tier, 56% sent to the balanced
tier and only 10% sent to performance.
You can see on the far left, kind of the different distribution
of costs for the always performance model versus the routed.
And then you can see on the right side,
for the routed threads, we had much cheaper fast runs
and then the performance runs.
And then on the right, you can see in aggregate,
the fast runs were much cheaper and then balanced
and performance more expensive accordingly.
One interesting note, we definitely
did see a couple of very long threads contributing
disproportionately to cost.
And this was true for both the routed and non-routed arms
of the experiment.
I will note, we actually started a second experiment,
which was router versus a controlled fast model.
So in the first experiment, it was
a control of the performance model.
We did end this test within a day
because we got so many complaints from users
who were stuck on the fast arm.
And so we got enough complaints.
we didn't want to significantly degrade user experience.
And so we decided to stop this experiment.
But it was pretty telling.
We certainly couldn't switch over to GLM-5.3-Flash
for all of the tasks that Open SWE needs to manage.
So what's next here?
There is definitely a lot that we could do to further explore
model routing optimizations.
I think the first thing would be benchmarking the router
on other eval sets like Deep SWE,
rather than just doing the A/B testing,
or even perhaps other benchmarks that are more review focused,
because generally the task for Open SWE
is to generate good, reviewable PRs.
The second thing that we didn't touch
is model selection for subagents.
So there's definitely more cost optimizations to be made
if we also select appropriately sized models
for the subagents that the main agent orchestrates
with the Deep Agents harness.
A third thing that I mentioned earlier
we could certainly explore is rerouting mid-thread.
So you can imagine if for Open SWE, a user asks a question
and then discovers that maybe a pretty complex bug fix is
in order or wants to design a new feature mid-thread,
you might want to upgrade to a more capable model.
And rerouting mid-thread could help
to ensure that the right model is
chosen for the task at any point in the given thread.
One trade-off here is that if you do switch a model,
you experience a cache miss, which can be costly.
But for async agents like Open SWE,
there's actually a lot of cache misses anyways,
just because there's more than a five minute idle time
between when an agent responds
and a developer has time to respond back in Slack.
So this cache miss might actually not
be a super significant concern.
And then the fourth thing would be
digging for richer routing signals.
So we didn't get a ton of feedback on traces.
We did get, you know, the PR merge rate
was a very reliable metric,
but trying to get more active feedback
would be helpful as well.
All right, so if you want to get started
building your own router,
I would recommend following the four steps
that we did in this experiment.
So one, understand your agent's task space.
Two, pick models along the Pareto frontier,
the cost intelligence curve.
Third, treat routing as context engineering
and build your router into the harness
where the appropriate context is
for the given tasks at hand.
And fourth, make sure you have the power to measure success
before you begin live routing.
You can easily add routing to your own agent
with our model routing middleware.
And at LangChain, we've always prided ourselves
on offering open source software
that's model provider agnostic.
And so changing models in your router
should just be a one line of code change.
You can also check out Open SWE at langchain-ai/open-swe
on GitHub.
You can learn more about building a harness with Jev,
which is a decision model that's incredibly powerful
for the model routing step at the blog linked below.
And we always love hearing from you.
Feel free to tag us @LangChain on X.
Thanks for watching and see you in the next one.